<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The funerals of the high and mighty Prince Henry, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornewaile and Rothsay, Count Palatine of Chester, Earle of Carick, and late Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter VVhich noble Prince deceased at St. Iames, the sixt day of Nouember, 1612. and was most princely interred the seuenth day of December following, within the Abbey of Westminster, in the eighteenth yeere of his age.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103976</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839718</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4165</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03017)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1381:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The funerals of the high and mighty Prince Henry, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornewaile and Rothsay, Count Palatine of Chester, Earle of Carick, and late Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter VVhich noble Prince deceased at St. Iames, the sixt day of Nouember, 1612. and was most princely interred the seuenth day of December following, within the Abbey of Westminster, in the eighteenth yeere of his age.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Iohn Budgde [i.e. Budge], and are to be sould at his shop at the great south dore of Paules, and at Brittanes Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</note>
                  <note>The last page bears a woodcut within a black frame.</note>
                  <note>Usually found as part 2 of: Chapman, George.  An epicede or funerall song: London, 1612.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612 --  Death and burial --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:1"/>
                  <p>FVNERALS OF THE HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE <hi>HENRY,</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornewaile</hi> and <hi>Rothſay,</hi> Count Palatine of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Earle of <hi>Carick,</hi> and late KNIGHT of the moſt Noble Order of the GARTER.</p>
                  <p>Vhich Noble <hi>Prince</hi> deceaſed at S. <hi>James,</hi> the ſixt day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> 1612. and was moſt Princely interred the ſeuenth day of <hi>December</hi> following, within the <hi>Abbey</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeere of his AGE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop at the great ſouth dore of <hi>Paulles,</hi> and at Brittanes Burſſe. 161<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:2"/>
                  <head>THE FVNERALS OF THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE <hi>HENRY,</hi> Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornewaile</hi> and <hi>Rothſay,</hi> Count Palatine of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Earle of Carick, and late Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the GARTER.</head>
                  <head type="sub">VVhich Noble Prince deceaſed at Saint IAMES, the 6. day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> 1612. and was moſt Princely interred the 7. of <hi>December</hi> following, within the Abbey of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the Eighteenth yeere of his AGE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He body of the ſaid PRINCE being bowelled, enbalmed and cloſed vp in Lead, there were foure Chambers hung with blackes, <hi>viz.</hi> the Gaurd chamber and the Preſence with blacke Cloth, the Priuy Chamber with finer Cloth,
<pb facs="tcp:4165:3"/> and that which was his <hi>Highnes</hi> Bed-chamber, with blacke Veluet: in the middeſt whereof was ſet vp a Canopy of blacke Veluet, valanced, and fringed; vnder which vpon Treſſels the Coffin with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the PRINCE was placed, couered with a large pall of blacke Veluet, and adorned with Scu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chions of his <hi>Armes.</hi> Vpon the head of which Coſſin was layde a Cuſhion of blacke Veluet, and his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> Cap and Coronet ſet thereon, as alſo his Robes of eſtate, Sword and Rod of Gould; and ſo it remayned (being daily and nightly watched) vntill two or three dayes before his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals. In which time euery day, both Morning and Euening Prayers were ſaid in his Preſence or Priuy Chamber, by his Chaplaines, and his Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and chiefe Officers attendant thereat.</p>
                  <p>Thurſday before the Funeralls his Princely bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was brought forth of his Bed-chamber into his priuie chamber.</p>
                  <p>Friday, it was brought into his Preſence-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and ſet vnder his cloath of eſtate.</p>
                  <p>Satterday, the fift of <hi>December,</hi> about three of the clocke in the after-noone it was remoued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Guard-chamber, where all his chiefe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and Officers being aſſembled, and the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Armes in their Coates, the corps was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempnly carried into the Chappell of that houſe, and placed vnder a canopy in the middeſt of the Quire, the Biſhop of Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h-field red the Seruice, and the Gentlemen of the Kings Chappell, with
<pb facs="tcp:4165:3"/> the children thereof, ſung diuers excellent An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theams, together with the Organs, and other winde inſtruments, which likewiſe was performed the day following, being Sunday.</p>
                  <p>Munday, the 7. of <hi>December,</hi> (the Funerall day) the repreſentation was layd vpon the Corps, and both together put into an open Chariot, and ſo proceeded as followeth:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pooremen,</hi> in gownes, to the number of 140.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>About</hi> 300.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Gentlemens ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Eſquires ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Knights ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Baronets ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Barons ſonnes ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Viſcount ſonnes ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rles ſonnes ſeruants.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Two <hi>Drummes</hi> and a <hi>Fife,</hi> their Drummes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with blacke cloth, and Scuchions of the Prince his Armes therevpon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Porteſmou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h,</hi> Purſuiuant of Armes.</p>
                  <p>The great Standard of Prince HENRY, being a <hi>Lyon</hi> crowned, ſtanding on a <hi>Chappeau,</hi> borne by Sir <hi>Iohn Win,</hi> KNIGHT and Baronet, the Motto therein, <hi>Fax ment is honeſtae gloria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4165:4"/>
                        <hi>About</hi> 306.</label>
                     <item>Prince HENRY his Houſhold Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, according to their ſeuerall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Degrees: with Tradeſ-men and Artificers that belonged vnto his Highneſſe.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Trumpets.</p>
                  <p>The Coronet of the Prince, being the three Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in a Crownet, with his Motto; <hi>Iuuat ire per altum;</hi> borne by Sir <hi>Roger Dalliſon,</hi> Knight and Baronet.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>About</hi> 360.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Barons ſeruants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </item>
                           <item>Viſcounts ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Earles ſeruants: as well Engliſh as</item>
                           <item>Strangers.</item>
                           <item>The Duke of <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                                    <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi> his ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>The Lord Chauncellors ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Count <hi>Henry de Naſsa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi> his ſeruants.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Trumpets.</p>
                  <p>A Banner of th'Earledome of <hi>Carick,</hi> borne by Sir <hi>Dauid Fowles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Horſe led by a Quirry of the Stable; the Horſe was couered with blacke cloath, and armed with Scuchions of that Earledome, hauing his Cheiffron and Plumes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4165:4"/>
                        <hi>About</hi> 80.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Archbiſhops ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> his ſeruants.</item>
                           <item>Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his ſeruants.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Blew-mantle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mes.</p>
                  <p>A Banner of the Earledome of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> borne by the Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Effingham.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Horſe led by a Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry of the Stable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> couered with blacke cloath, and armed with Scuchions of that Earledome, his Cheiffron and Plumes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>About</hi> 40.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Faulconer and Huntſmen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the workes.</item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the Poultry.</item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the Larder.</item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the Spicary.</item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the Kitchen.</item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>Clearkes of the Wardrobe.</item>
                           <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of the Workes.</item>
                           <item>Pay M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</item>
                           <item>And Cleark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Comptroller.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4165:5"/>
                        <hi>About</hi> 60.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Seriants of the Veſtry.</item>
                           <item>Children of the Chappell.</item>
                           <item>Gentlemen of the Chappell in rich Copes.</item>
                           <item>Muſitians.</item>
                           <item>Apothecaries and Surgions.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <item>Doctors of Phyſicke.</item>
                     <label>24.</label>
                     <item>The Princes Chapleyns.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Portcullis Purſuyuant of Armes.</p>
                  <p>A Banner of the Dukedome of <hi>Rothſay,</hi> borne by the Lord <hi>Bruſe,</hi> Baron of <hi>Kinloſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Horſe led by a Quirry of the Stable, couered with blacke cloath, armed with Scuchions of that Dukedome, his Cheiffron and Plumes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>About</hi> 80.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Pages of the Chamber.</item>
                           <item>Gentlemen, the Princes ſeruants ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary.</item>
                           <item>The Princes Solicitor, and Counſell at Law.</item>
                           <item>Groome Porter.</item>
                           <item>Gentlemen Vſhers, quarter Waiters.</item>
                           <item>Groomes of the Priuy-Chamber ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary.</item>
                           <item>Groomes of the Priuy-Chamber in ordinary.</item>
                           <item>Groomes of the Bed-chamber.</item>
                           <item>Pages of the Bed-chamber, and the Princes owne Page.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:5"/>
                  <p> Rouge-Dragon Purſuyuant.</p>
                  <p>A Banner of the Dukedome of Cornewall, borne by the Lord <hi>Clifford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Horſe led by Mr. <hi>Henry Alexander,</hi> couered with blacke cloath, armed with Scuchions of that Dukedome, his Cheiffron and Plumes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>About</hi> 146.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Count <hi>Henrickes</hi> Gentlemen.</item>
                           <item>Count <hi>Palatines</hi> Gentlemen, <hi>viz.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <label>viz.</label>
                                 <item>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>Mounſieur <hi>Eltz.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Helmſtadt.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Colbe.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Benefer.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Adolſhein.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Nenzkin.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Walbron.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Waldgraue.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Factes.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Carden.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Berlinger.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Grorode.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Cawlt.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Stenſels.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Ridzell.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Helinger.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Henbell.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Auckenſten.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <pb facs="tcp:4165:6"/>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Gellu.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Wallyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Pellinger.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Berlipps.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Shott.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Weldenſten.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Crotleſemere.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Leuinsten.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Dathenes.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Colbe.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Scultetez.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Rampf.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Dawnſier.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Maier.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Mounſ. <hi>Wanebach.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his Gentlemen.</p>
                  <p>Gentlemen of Prince <hi>Henries</hi> Priuy-Chamber extraordinary.</p>
                  <p>Knights and Gentlemen of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Priuy-Chamber in ordinary, and of his Bed-Chamber, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and Cupbearers.</p>
                  <p>The Prince his Secretary.</p>
                  <p>The Prince his Threſorer of his Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. The Threſorer of his Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, and the Comptroller of his Houſhould together, bearing their white ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:6"/>
                  <p> Rong-croix Purſuyuant of Armes.</p>
                  <p>A Banner of the Princes Principalitie of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, with a Labell, borne by the Viſcount <hi>Fenton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Horſe led by Sir <hi>Sigiſmond Alexander,</hi> coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with blacke cloath, armed with Scuchions of that Kingdome, his Cheiffron and Plumes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Baronets.</item>
                     <item>Barons yonger ſonnes.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Edward Phillips,</hi> Mr. of the Roles, being the Prince his Chaunceller, going alone.</p>
                  <p>Knights Priuy Councellors to the KING: <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Herbart,</hi> Secretary.</item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Iulius Ceſar</hi> Chaunceller of the Exchequer.</item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Parry,</hi> Chaunceller of the Duchie of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Barons eldeſt ſonnes.</p>
                  <p>Three Trumpets.</p>
                  <p>Lancaſter Herauld.</p>
                  <p>A Banner of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with <hi>Wales,</hi> borne by the Viſcount <hi>Liſle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:7"/>
                  <p>A Horſe led by Sir <hi>William VVebb,</hi> Knight, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with blacke cloath, cloath, his Cheiffron and Plumes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Earles yonger ſonnes.</item>
                     <item>Viſcounts eldeſt ſonnes.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Barons of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <head>Barons of England: <hi>viz.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Kneuit.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Candiſh.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Arundell</hi> of <hi>VVardor.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Carewe.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Stanhop.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Denny.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Spencer.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Garrard.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Danvers.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Harington.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Peters.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Ruſſell.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>VVotton.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Knowles.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Norris.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Campton.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Hunſden.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Chandos.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Northe.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Darcy</hi> of <hi>Chich.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Sheffeild.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Rich.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>VVharton.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Evers.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>VVentworth.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>VVindeſor.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Mounteagle.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Dudley.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Stafford.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Dacres.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Morley.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lord <hi>Laware.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <label>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4165:7"/>
                        <hi>Biſhops</hi> 5.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Couentry</hi> and <hi>Lichfield.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Ely.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Earle of <hi>Exceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Prince his Chamberlayne, Sir <hi>Thomas Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loner,</hi> alone, bearing his white ſtaffe.</p>
                  <p>The Lord <hi>Chancellor,</hi> and Count <hi>Henricke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury:</hi> Preacher.</p>
                  <p>The great Embrodered Banner of the <hi>Vnion,</hi> borne by the Earles of <hi>Montgomery</hi> and <hi>Argyle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Horſe led, called <hi>Le Cheual de deul,</hi> couered with blacke Veluet, and ledde by a chiefe Quirry. <hi>Monſieur Sant Antoin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Prince his Hachments of HONOVR, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by Officers of Armes, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Spurres, by <hi>Windſor.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Gauntlets, by <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Helme and Creſt, by <hi>Richmond.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Targe, by <hi>Yorke.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Sword, by <hi>Norroy,</hi> King of Armes.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:8"/>
                  <p>The Coat, by <hi>Clarencieux,</hi> King of Armes.</p>
                  <p>Three Gentlemen Vſhers to the Prince, bearing their wands.</p>
                  <p>The Corps of the Prince, lying in an open Chariot, with the Princes repreſentation thereon, inueſted with his Robes of eſtate of Purple Veluet, furred with Ermines, his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> Cap and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet on his head, and his Rod of Gould in his hand, and at his feet, within the ſaid Chariot, ſat Sir <hi>Dauid Murrey,</hi> the Maſter of his Wardrobe.</p>
                  <p>The Chariot was couered with blacke Veluet, ſet with Plumes of blacke feathers, and drawne by ſixe Horſes couered, and Armed with Scuchions, hauing their Cheiffrons and Plumes.</p>
                  <p>A Canopy of blacke Veluet borne ouer the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation by ſixe Baronets.</p>
                  <p>Tenne Bannerols, borne about the body by ten Baronets.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Moyle Finch.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Mounſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Wentworth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Henry Sauile.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Brewdnell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Anthony Cope.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>George Greſley.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Robert Cotten.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Lewis Treſham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Phillip Tiruit.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:8"/>
                  <p>Foure Aſſiſtants to the Corps, that bore vp the corners of the Pall. <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 The Lord <hi>Zouch.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 The Lord <hi>Abergaueny.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 The Lord <hi>Burghley.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 The Lord <hi>Walden.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William Seger, Garter,</hi> Principall King of Armes, betweene the Gentleman-Viher of Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the Gentleman-Vſher of the Prince <hi>Palatine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prince</hi> CHARLES chiefe <hi>Mourner,</hi> ſupported by the Lord Priuy-Seale, and the Duke of <hi>Lenox.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His <hi>Highneſſe</hi> Traine was borne by the Lord <hi>Dawbney,</hi> Brother to the Duke of <hi>Lenox.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then followed the <hi>Prince Elector,</hi> FREDERICK, Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His <hi>Highneſſe</hi> Traine was borne by <hi>Mounſieur Shamburgh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Twelue Earles Aſſiſtants to the chiefe <hi>Mourner, viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Shrewſbury.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Rutland.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Southampton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Hartford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Dorſet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Pembroke.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle of <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:9"/>
                  <p>Earles ſtrangers, attendants on Count <hi>Palatine,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Count <hi>VVigenſten.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Lewis de Naſſau.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Leuingſten.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Hodenlo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Ringraue.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Erback.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Naſſaw. Scarburg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Le Hanow,</hi> Iunior.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Pages.</head>
                           <item>Count <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>berſh.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Count <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>olmes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Count <hi>Zerottin.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Horſe of Eſtate, led by Sir <hi>Robert Dowglas,</hi> Maiſter of the Princes Horſe.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Palzgreaues</hi> Priuy-Counſellors, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Count of <hi>Solmes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mounſieur <hi>Shouburgh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mounſieur <hi>de Pleſhau.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mounſieur <hi>Helmestedt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mounſ. <hi>Shouburgh,</hi> Iunior.</item>
                     <item>Mounſ. <hi>Landſhat.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Officers and Groomes of Prince <hi>Henries</hi> ſtable. <hi>The Guard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Knight <hi>Marſhall,</hi> and twenty ſeruants that kept order in the proceeding.</p>
                  <p>Diuers Knights and Gentlemen, the Kings ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants that came in voluntary in blacks. So that the whole number amounted to 2000. or thereabout.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:9"/>
                  <p>AN EPICEDE <hi>OR Funerall Song:</hi> On the moſt diſaſtrous Death, of the High-borne <hi>Prince</hi> of Men, <hi>HENRY</hi> Prince of WALES, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With</hi> The Funeralls, and Repreſentation of the Herſe of the ſame High and mighty Prince; Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornewaile</hi> and <hi>Rothſay,</hi> Count Palatine of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Earle of <hi>Carick,</hi> and late Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the GARTER.</p>
                  <p>Which Noble <hi>Prince</hi> deceaſed at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>James,</hi> the ſixt day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> 1612. and was moſt Princely interred the ſeuenth day of <hi>December</hi> following, within the Abbey of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeere of his Age.</p>
                  <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to bee ſould at his ſhop at the great ſouth dore of <hi>Paules,</hi> and at Brittanes Burſſe. 161<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:10"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:10"/>
                  <head>TO MY AFFECTIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NATE, AND TRVE Friend, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Jones.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My trueſt Friend:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE most vnualuable and diſmaifull hope of my moſt deare and Heroicall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone, Prince <hi>HENRY,</hi> hath ſo ſtricken all my ſpirits to the earth, that I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more dare, to looke vp to any great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but reſoluing the little reſt of my poore life to obſcuritie, and the ſhadow of his death; prepare euer hereafter, for the light of heauen.</p>
                  <p>So abſolute, conſtant, and noble, your loue hath beene to mee; that if I ſhould not as effectually, by all my beſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, acknowledge it; I could neither ſatisfie mine owne affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, nor deſerue yours.</p>
                  <p>Accept therefore, as freely as I acknowledge, this vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſigne of my loue; till God bleſsing my future labours, I may adde a full end, to whatſoeuer is begunne in your aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my requitall. A little, bleſt, makes a great feast (my best friend) and therefore deſpaire not, but that, out of that little, our loues alwayes made euen, may make you ſay, you
<pb facs="tcp:4165:11"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> rather beene happy in your kindneſſe, then in the least degree, hurt. There may fauours paſſe betwixt poore friends, which euen the richeſt, and greateſt may enuy. And <hi>GOD</hi> that yet neuer let me liue, I know will neuer let me die an empaire to any friend. If any good, more then requitall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, it is all yours as freely, as euer yours was mine; in which noble freedome and alacritie of doing; you haue thrice done, all I acknowledge. And thus knowing, I giue you little contentment, in this ſo farre vnexpected publication of my gratitude; I rest ſatisfied with the ingenuous diſcharge of mine owne office. Your extraordinary and noble loue and ſorrow, borne to our moſt ſweet <hi>PRINCE,</hi> entitles you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to this Dedication: which (with my generall Loue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly proteſted to your whole Name and Family) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude you as deſertfull of, at my hands, as our Nobleſt Earle; and ſo euer remaine</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt true poore Friend, GEO: CHAPMAN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:11"/>
                  <head>AN EPICED, <hi>OR Funerall Song:</hi> On the moſt diſaſtrous Death, of the High-borne <hi>Prince</hi> of Men, <hi>HENRY</hi> Prince of WALES, &amp;c.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF euer aduerſe Influence enui'd</l>
                     <l>The glory of our Lands, or tooke a pride</l>
                     <l>To trample on our height; or in the Eye</l>
                     <l>Strooke all the pomp of Principalitie,</l>
                     <l>Now it hath done ſo; Oh, if euer Heauen</l>
                     <l>Made with the earth his angry reckening euen,</l>
                     <l>Now it hath done ſo. Euer, euer be</l>
                     <l>Admir'd, and fear'd, that Triple Maieſtie</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe finger could ſo eaſily ſticke a Fate,</l>
                     <l>Twixt leaſt Felicity, and greateſt ſtate;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:12"/>
                     <l>Such, as ſhould melt our ſhore into a Sea,</l>
                     <l>And dry our Ocean with Calamitie.</l>
                     <l>Heauen open'd, and but ſhow'd him to our eies,</l>
                     <l>Then ſhut againe, and ſhow'd our Miſeries.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O God, to what end are thy Graces giuen?<note place="margin">Expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batione.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Onely to ſhow the world, Men fit for Heauen,</l>
                     <l>Then rauiſh them, as if too good for Earth?</l>
                     <l>VVe know, the moſt exempt in wealth, power, Birth,</l>
                     <l>Or any other bleſſing; ſhould employ</l>
                     <l>(As to their chiefe end) all things they enioy,</l>
                     <l>To make them fit for Heauen; and not purſue</l>
                     <l>VVith hearty appetite, the damned crue</l>
                     <l>Of meerely ſenſuall and earth ye pleaſures?</l>
                     <l>But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one hath done ſo; ſhal ſtrait the treſures</l>
                     <l>Digg'd to, in thoſe deeps, be conſum'd by death?</l>
                     <l>Shall not the reſt, that error ſwalloweth,</l>
                     <l>Be, by the Patterne of that Maſter-peece,</l>
                     <l>Help't to inſtruct their erring faculties?</l>
                     <l>VVhen, without cleare example; euen the beſt</l>
                     <l>(That cannot put by knowledge to the Teſt</l>
                     <l>what they are taught) ſerue like the worſt in field?</l>
                     <l>Is power to force, who will not freely yield,</l>
                     <l>(Being great aſſiſtant, to diuine example)</l>
                     <l>As vaine a Pillar to thy Manly Temple?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:12"/>
                     <l>when (without perfect knowledge, which ſcarce one</l>
                     <l>Of many kingdoms reach) no other ſtone</l>
                     <l>Man hath to build one corner of thy Phane,</l>
                     <l>Saue one of theſe? But when the deſperate wane<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Potentia expers ſapi entiae quo maior eſt, eo pernicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſior: ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia procul à potentia manca vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur.</hi> Pla</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of power, and of example to all good,</l>
                     <l>So ſpent is, that one cannot turne the flood,</l>
                     <l>Of goodnes, gainſt her ebbe; but both muſt plie,</l>
                     <l>And be at full to; or her ſtreame will drie;</l>
                     <l>VVhere ſhall they meete againe, now he is gone</l>
                     <l>Where both went foot by foot; &amp; both were one?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>One that in hope, tooke vp to topleſſe height</l>
                     <l>All his great Anceſtors; his one ſaile, freight</l>
                     <l>VVith all, all Princes treaſures; he like one</l>
                     <l>Of no importance; no way built vpon,</l>
                     <l>Vaniſht vvithout the end, for vvhich he had</l>
                     <l>Such matchleſſe vertues, &amp; was God-like made?</l>
                     <l>Haue thy beſt vvorkes no better cauſe t'expreſſe</l>
                     <l>Themſelues like men, and thy true Images?</l>
                     <l>To toile in vertues ſtudy, to ſuſtaine</l>
                     <l>(vvith comfort for her) want, &amp; ſhame, &amp; paine;</l>
                     <l>No nobler end in this life, then a death</l>
                     <l>Timeles, and wretched, wrought with leſſe then breath?</l>
                     <l>And nothing ſolide, worthy of our ſoules?</l>
                     <l>Nothing that Reaſon, more then Senſe extols!</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:13"/>
                     <l>Nothing that may in perfect iudgement be</l>
                     <l>A fit foote for our Crowne eternitie?</l>
                     <l>All which, thou ſeem'ſt to tell vs, in this one</l>
                     <l>Killing diſcomfort; apt to make our mone</l>
                     <l>Conclude gainſt all things, ſerious and good;</l>
                     <l>our ſelues, not thy forms, but Chymaeras brood.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chymaera,</hi> a monſter, hauing his head and breſt like a Lyon; his belly like a Got<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>; and taile like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Dragon.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now Princes, dare ye boaſt your vig'rous ſtates</l>
                     <l>That Fortunes breath thus builds and ruinates?</l>
                     <l>Exalt your ſpirits? truſt in flowry youth?</l>
                     <l>Giue reynes to pleaſure? all your humors ſooth?</l>
                     <l>Licence in rapine? Powers exempt from lawes?</l>
                     <l>Contempt of all things, but your own applauſe?</l>
                     <l>And think your ſwindge to any tyranny giuen,</l>
                     <l>VVill ſtretch as broad, &amp; laſt as long as heauen;</l>
                     <l>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that curb'd with vertues hand his powre</l>
                     <l>his youth with continence; his ſweet with ſowre</l>
                     <l>Boldnes with pious feare; his pallats height</l>
                     <l>Applied to health, and not to appetite;</l>
                     <l>Felt timeles ſicknes charge; ſtate, power to flie,</l>
                     <l>And glutted Death with all his crueltie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Partiall deuourer euer of the beſt,<note place="margin">To Death.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVith headlong rapture, ſparing long the reſt</l>
                     <l>Could not the precious teares his Father ſhed,</l>
                     <l>(That are with Kingdomes to be ranſomed?)</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:13"/>
                     <l>His Bleeding prayer, vpon his knees t'implore,<note place="margin">The Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the King in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſickne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That if for any ſinne of his, Heauen tore</l>
                     <l>From his moſt Royall body that chiefe Limme,</l>
                     <l>It might be ranſom'd, for the reſt of Him?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Could not the ſacred eies thou didſt prophane</l>
                     <l>In his great Mothers teares? The ſpightful bane</l>
                     <l>Thou pour'dſt vpon the cheeks of al the Graces</l>
                     <l>In his more gracious Siſters? The defaces</l>
                     <l>(with all the Furies ouer-flowing Galles)</l>
                     <l>Curſedly fronting her neere Nuptials?</l>
                     <l>Could not, O could not, the Almighty ruth</l>
                     <l>Of all theſe force thee to forbeare the youth</l>
                     <l>Of our Incomparable Prince of Men?</l>
                     <l>whoſe Age had made thy Iron Forcke his Pen,</l>
                     <l>T'eterniſe what it now doth murder meerely;</l>
                     <l>And ſhal haue from my ſoule, my curſes yerely.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tyrant, what knew'ſt thou, but the barbarous wound</l>
                     <l>Thou gau'ſt the ſon, the Father might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found?</l>
                     <l>Both liu'd ſo mixtly, and were ioyntly One,</l>
                     <l>Spirit to ſpirit cleft. The Humor bred</l>
                     <l>In one heart, ſtraight was with the other fed;</l>
                     <l>The bloud of one, the others heart did fire;</l>
                     <l>The heart and humour, were the Sonne &amp; Sire;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:14"/>
                     <l>The heart yet, void of humors ſlender'ſt part,</l>
                     <l>May eaſier liue, then humour without heart;</l>
                     <l>The Riuer needes the helpfull fountaine euer,</l>
                     <l>More then the Fountaine, the ſupplyed Riuer.</l>
                     <l>As th Iron then, when it hath once put on<note place="margin">Sim l.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Magnets qualitie, to the vertuous Stone</l>
                     <l>Is euer drawne, and not the ſtone to it:</l>
                     <l>So may the heauens, the ſonnes Fate, not admit<note place="margin">Apodeſis.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To draw the Fathers, till a hundred yeeres</l>
                     <l>Haue drown'd that Iſſue to him in our teares.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bleſt yet, and ſacred ſhall thy memory be,<note place="margin">Reditio ad Principem.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O-nothing-leſſe-then-mortall Deitie.</l>
                     <l>Thy Graces, like the Sunne, to all men giuing;</l>
                     <l>Fatall to thee in death, but kill me liuing.</l>
                     <l>Now, as inuerted, like th <hi>Antipodes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The world (in all things of deſert to pleaſe)</l>
                     <l>Is falne on vs, with thee: thy ruines lye</l>
                     <l>On our burſt boſomes, as if from the skye</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Day-ſtar,</hi> greater then the world were driuen</l>
                     <l>Suncke to the Earth, and left a hole in Heauen;</l>
                     <l>throgh which, a ſecod deluge now poures down</l>
                     <l>On our poore Earth; in which are ouer-flowne met</l>
                     <l>The ſeeds of all the ſacred Vertues, ſet</l>
                     <l>In his Spring-Court; where all the prime ſpirits</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:14"/>
                     <l>Of all our Kingdomes; as if from the death,<note place="margin">Thoſe that came to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeruice ſeem'd (compared with the places they leu'd in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) to the from death to the fields of life, in tending the beſt part of yong and noble Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That in men liuing; baſenes and rapine ſheath,</l>
                     <l>VVhere they before liu'd, they vnwares were come</l>
                     <l>Into a free, and freſh <hi>Eliſitum;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Caſting regenerate, and refined eyes</l>
                     <l>On him that rais'd them from their graues of vice,</l>
                     <l>Digg'd in their old grounds, to ſpring freſh on thoſe</l>
                     <l>That his diuine Ideas did propoſe,</l>
                     <l>Firſt to himſelfe; &amp; then would forme in them.</l>
                     <l>VVho did not thirſt to plant his ſonne neer him</l>
                     <l>as neer the <hi>Thames</hi> their houſes? what one worth</l>
                     <l>VVas there in all our world, that ſet not forth</l>
                     <l>All his deſerts, to Pilgrime to his fauors,</l>
                     <l>VVith all deuotion, offering all his labors?</l>
                     <l>And how the wilde Bore, Barbariſme, now</l>
                     <l>will roote theſe Quick-ſets vp? what hearb ſhall grow,</l>
                     <l>that is not ſown in his inhumane tracts?</l>
                     <l>No thought of good ſhall ſpring, but many acts</l>
                     <l>Will crop, or blaſt, or blow it vp: and ſee<note place="margin">The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Princes Seruants.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>How left to this, the mournfull Familie,</l>
                     <l>Muffled in black clouds, full of teares are driuen</l>
                     <l>With ſtormes about the relickes of this Heauen;</l>
                     <l>Retiring from the world, like Corſes, herſt</l>
                     <l>Home to their graues, a hundred waies diſperſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:15"/>
                     <l>O that this court-ſchoole; this <hi>Olimpus</hi> meerly,<note place="margin">The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces houſe an Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, where all conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues were practiſed.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhere two-fold Man was practisde; ſhould ſo early</l>
                     <l>Diſſolue the celebration purpos'd there,</l>
                     <l>Of all <hi>Heroique</hi> parts, when farre and neere,</l>
                     <l>All were reſolu'd t'admire, None to contend,</l>
                     <l>VVhen, in the place of all, one wretched end</l>
                     <l>VVill take vp all endeauours; Harpye Gaine,</l>
                     <l>Pandare to Gote, Ambition; goulden Chaine<note place="margin">Non Homeri Aurea Reſtis</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To true mans freedome; not from heau'n let fal</l>
                     <l>To draw men vp; But ſhot from Hell to hale</l>
                     <l>All men, as bondſlaues, to his Turckiſh den,</l>
                     <l>For Toades, and Adders, far more fit then men.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>His houſe had well his ſurname from a <hi>Saint,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his houſe.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>All things ſo ſacred, did ſo liuely paint</l>
                     <l>Their pious figures in it: And as well</l>
                     <l>His other houſe, did in his Name fore-tell<note place="margin">Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>what it ſhould harbour; a rich world of parts</l>
                     <l>Bonfire-like kindling, the ſtill-feaſted Arts,</l>
                     <l>which now on bridles bite, and puft Contempt</l>
                     <l>Spurres to Deſpaire, from all fit foode exempt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O what a frame of Good, in all hopes rais'd</l>
                     <l>Came tumbling downe with him! as when was ſeiſde</l>
                     <l>By Grecian furie, famous <hi>Jlion,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhoſe fall, ſtill rings out his Confuſion.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:15"/>
                     <l>VVhat <hi>Triumphs,</hi> ſcatterd at his feete, lye ſmoking!</l>
                     <l>Banquets that will not downe; their cherers choking,</l>
                     <l>Fields fought, and hidden now, with future ſlaughter,</l>
                     <l>Furies ſit frowning, where late fat ſweet laughter,</l>
                     <l>The actiue lying maim'd, the healthfull craſde?</l>
                     <l>All round about his Herſe? And how amaz'd</l>
                     <l>The change of things ſtands! how aſtoniſhtioy</l>
                     <l>VVonders he euer was? yet euery Toy</l>
                     <l>Quits this graue loſſe: Rainbowes no ſooner taint</l>
                     <l>Thinne dewye vapors, which oppos'd beames paint</l>
                     <l>Round in an inſtant, (at which children ſtare</l>
                     <l>And ſlight the Sunne, that makes them circular</l>
                     <l>And ſo diſparent) then mere gawds peirce men,</l>
                     <l>Slighting the graue, like fooles, and children.</l>
                     <l>So courtly nere plagues, ſooth and ſtupefie</l>
                     <l>And vvith ſuch paine, men leaue ſelfe flatterie.</l>
                     <l>Of vvhich, to ſee him free (who ſtood no leſſe<note place="margin">The Prince not to be wrought on by flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then a full ſiege of ſuch) who can expreſſe</l>
                     <l>His moſt direct infuſion from aboue,</l>
                     <l>Farre from the humorous ſeede of mortal loue?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He knew, that Iuſtice ſimply vſd, vvas beſt,<note place="margin">His know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and wiſdome.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Made princes moſt ſecure, moſt lou'd, moſt bleſt</l>
                     <l>No Artezan; No Scholler; could pretend,</l>
                     <l>No Stateſman; No Diuine; for his owne end</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:16"/>
                     <l>Anything to him, but he vvould deſcend</l>
                     <l>The depth of any right belong'd to it,</l>
                     <l>Where they could merit, or himſelfe ſhould quit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He would not truſt, with what himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd,</l>
                     <l>Any in any kinde; but euer learn'd</l>
                     <l>The grounds of what he built on: Nothing lies<note place="margin">Any man is capable of his ovvn fit courſe and office in any thing.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>In mans fit courſe, that his own knowledge flies</l>
                     <l>Eyther direct, or circumſtantiall.</l>
                     <l>O what are Princes then, that neuer call</l>
                     <l>Their actions to account, but flatterers truſt</l>
                     <l>To make their triall, if vniuſt or iuſt?</l>
                     <l>Flatterers are houſhold theeues, traitors by law,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Apoſtrophe.</hi> Men grovv ſo vgly by truſting flattery vvith their informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that vvhen they ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their eyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard, they caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay vvith their ovvne lothing.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>that rob kings honors, &amp; their ſoules-bloud draw;</l>
                     <l>Diſeaſes, that keep nouriſhment from their food.</l>
                     <l>And as to know himſelfe, is mans chiefe good,</l>
                     <l>So that vvhich intercepts that ſupreame skill,</l>
                     <l>(which Flattery is) is the ſupreameſt ill:</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe lookes will breede the Baſilisk in kings eyes,</l>
                     <l>That by reflexion of his ſight, dyes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Simb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> And as a Nurſe lab'ring a vvayward Childe,</l>
                     <l>Day, and night watching it, like an offspring wilde;</l>
                     <l>Talkes infinitely idly to it ſtill;</l>
                     <l>Sings with a ſtanding throate, to worſe from ill;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:16"/>
                     <l>Lord-bleſſes it; beares with his pewks and cryes;</l>
                     <l>And to giue it a long lifes miſeries,</l>
                     <l>Sweetens his food, rocks, kiſſes, ſings againe;</l>
                     <l>Plyes it with rattles, and all obiects vaine:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So Flatterers, with as ſeruile childiſh things,</l>
                     <l>Obſerue, &amp; ſooth the waiward moods of kings;</l>
                     <l>So kings, that flatterers loue, had neede to haue</l>
                     <l>as nurſe-like councellors, &amp; contemn the graue;</l>
                     <l>Themſelues as wayward, and as noiſome too;</l>
                     <l>Full as vntuneable in all they doe,</l>
                     <l>As poore ſicke Infants; euer breeding Teeth</l>
                     <l>In all their humours, that be worſe then Death.</l>
                     <l>How wiſe then was our Prince that hated theſe,</l>
                     <l>and wold with nought but truth his humor pleſe</l>
                     <l>Nor would hee giue a place, but where hee ſaw</l>
                     <l>One that could vſe it; and become a Law</l>
                     <l>Both to his fortunes, and his Princes Honor.</l>
                     <l>Who wold giue <hi>fortune</hi> noght ſhe took vpon her,</l>
                     <l>Not giue but to deſert; nor take a chance,</l>
                     <l>That might not iuſtly, his vviſht ends aduance.</l>
                     <l>His Good he ioyn'd with Equitie and Truth;</l>
                     <l>VViſedome in yeeres, crown'd his ripe head in youth;</l>
                     <l>His heart wore all the folds of Policie,</l>
                     <l>Yet went as naked as Simplicitie.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:17"/>
                     <l>Knew good and ill; but onely good did loue;</l>
                     <l>In him the Serpent did embrace the Doue.</l>
                     <l>Hee was not curious to ſound all the ſtreame</l>
                     <l>Of others acts, yet kept his owne from them:</l>
                     <l>"He whoſe moſt darke deeds dare not ſtand the light,</l>
                     <l>"Begot was of impoſture and the night.</l>
                     <l>"VVho ſurer then a Man, doth ends ſecure;</l>
                     <l>"Eyther a God is, or a Diuell ſure.</l>
                     <l>The Preſident of men, whom (as men can)</l>
                     <l>All men ſhould imitate, was God and Man.</l>
                     <l>In theſe eleere deepes our Prince fiſh't troubl'd ſtreams</l>
                     <l>of bloud &amp; vantage challenge diadems.</l>
                     <l>In ſumme, (knot-like) hee was together put,</l>
                     <l>That no man could diſſolue, and ſo was cut,</l>
                     <l>But we ſhal ſee our foule-mouth'd factions ſpite</l>
                     <l>(Markt, witch-like, with one blacke eie, th'other</l>
                     <l>Ope, &amp; oppoſe againſt this ſpotleſſe ſun; (white)</l>
                     <l>Such, he auen ſtrike blinder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th'eclipſed moon</l>
                     <l>Twixt whom and nobleſſe, or humanities truth,</l>
                     <l>As much dull earth lies, and as little ruth,</l>
                     <l>(Should all things ſacred periſh) as there lyes</l>
                     <l>Twixt <hi>Phaebe,</hi> and the Light-fount of the skies,</l>
                     <l>In her moſt darke delinquence: vermine right,</l>
                     <l>That prey in darkneſſe, and abhorre the light;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:17"/>
                     <l>Liue by the ſpoile of vertue; are not well</l>
                     <l>But when they heare news, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their father hell</l>
                     <l>Of ſome blacke miſchiefe; neuer do good deed,</l>
                     <l>But where it does much harme, or hath no need.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What ſhall become of vertues far-ſhort traine,</l>
                     <l>when thou their head art reacht, high Prince of men?</l>
                     <l>O that thy life could haue diſperſt deaths ſtormes,</l>
                     <l>To giue faire act to thoſe Heroique formes,</l>
                     <l>with which al good rules had enricht thy mind,</l>
                     <l>Preparing for affayres of euery kinde;</l>
                     <l>Peace being but a pauſe to brearhe fierce warre;</l>
                     <l>No warrant dormant, to neglect his Starre;</l>
                     <l>The licence ſence hath, is t'informe the ſoule;</l>
                     <l>Not to ſuppreſſe her, and our luſts extoll;</l>
                     <l>This life in all things, to enioy the next;</l>
                     <l>Of which lawes, thy youth, both contain'd the text</l>
                     <l>And the contents; ah, that thy grey-ripe yeeres</l>
                     <l>Had made of all, <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Commentares,</l>
                     <l>(More then can now be thought) in fact t'enroule;</l>
                     <l>And make blacke Faction bluſh away her ſoule.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That, as a Temple, built when Pietie<note place="margin">Simil.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did to diuine ends offer ſpecially,</l>
                     <l>What men enjoy'd; that wondrous ſtate expreſt,</l>
                     <l>Strange Art, ſtrange coſt; yet who had intereſt</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:18"/>
                     <l>In all the frame of it; and ſaw thoſe dayes,</l>
                     <l>Admir'd but little; and as little praiſe</l>
                     <l>Gaue to the goodly Fabricke: but when men,</l>
                     <l>That liue whole Ages after, view it, then,</l>
                     <l>They gaze, and wonder; and the longer time</l>
                     <l>It ſtands, the more it glorifies his prime;</l>
                     <l>Growes freſh in honor, and the age doth ſhame</l>
                     <l>That in ſuch Monuments neglect ſuch fame;</l>
                     <l>So had thy ſacred Frame beene rais'd to height,</l>
                     <l>Forme, fulneſſe, ornament: the more the light</l>
                     <l>Had giuen it view, the more had Men admir'd;</l>
                     <l>And tho men now are ſcarce to warmneſſe fir'd</l>
                     <l>VVith loue of thee; but rather colde and dead</l>
                     <l>To all ſenſe of the grace they forfeited</l>
                     <l>In thy neglect, and loſſe; yet after-ages</l>
                     <l>VVould be inflam'd, and put on holy rages</l>
                     <l>with thy inſpiring vertues; curſing thoſe</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe breaths dare blaſt thus, in the bud, the Roſe.</l>
                     <l>But thou (woe's me) art blown vp before blowne,</l>
                     <l>And as the ruines of ſome famous Towne,</l>
                     <l>Show here a Temple ſtood; a Pallace, here;</l>
                     <l>A Cytadell, an Amphitheater;</l>
                     <l>Of which (ahlas) ſome broken Arches, ſtill</l>
                     <l>(Pillars, or Columnsrac't; which Art did fill</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:18"/>
                     <l>VVith all her riches and Diuinitie)</l>
                     <l>Retaine their great, and vvorthy memory:</l>
                     <l>So of our Princes ſtate, I nought rehearſe</l>
                     <l>But ſhow his ruines, bleeding in my verſe.</l>
                     <l>What poiſon'd Aſt'riſme, may his death accuſe?</l>
                     <l>Tell thy aſtoniſht Prophet (deathles Muſe)</l>
                     <l>And make my ſtarres therein, the more aduerſe,</l>
                     <l>The more aduance, vvith ſacred rage my Verſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſo adorne my deareſt Fautors Herſe.</l>
                     <l>That all the wits prophane, of theſe bold times</l>
                     <l>May feare to ſpend the ſpawne of their rancke rymes</l>
                     <l>On any touch of him, that ſhold be ſung</l>
                     <l>To eares diuine, and aske an Angels tongue.</l>
                     <l>VVith this it thundred; and a lightning ſhow'd</l>
                     <l>VVhere ſhe ſate writing in a ſable cloud;</l>
                     <l>A Penne ſo hard and ſharpe expreſt her plight,</l>
                     <l>It bit through Flint; and did in Diamant write;</l>
                     <l>Her vvords, ſhe ſung, and laid out ſuch a breſt,</l>
                     <l>As melted Heauen, and vext the very bleſt.</l>
                     <l>In which ſhe cal'd all worlds to her complaints,<note place="margin">Muſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And how our loſſe grew, thus vvith teares ſhee paints:<note place="margin">The cauſe and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                              <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hear earth &amp; heauen (&amp; you that haue no eares)</l>
                     <l>Hell, and the hearts of tyrants, heare my teares</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:19"/>
                     <l>Thus Brittaine <hi>Henry</hi> tooke his timeleſſe end;</l>
                     <l>VVhen his great Father did ſo far tranſcend</l>
                     <l>All other Kings; and that he had a Sonne</l>
                     <l>In all his Fathers gifts, ſo farre begunne,</l>
                     <l>As added to <hi>Fames</hi> Pynions, double wings;</l>
                     <l>And (as braue riuers, broken from their ſprings,</l>
                     <l>The further off, grow greater, and diſdaine</l>
                     <l>To ſpread a narrower current then the Maine)</l>
                     <l>Had drawne in all deſerts ſuch ample Spheares,</l>
                     <l>As Hope yet neuer turn'd about his yeeres.</l>
                     <l>All other Princes with his parts comparing;</l>
                     <l>Like all Heauens pettie Luminaries faring,</l>
                     <l>To radiant <hi>Lucifer,</hi> the dayes firſt borne)</l>
                     <l>It hurld a fire red as a threatning Morne<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ſia</hi> (Goddeſſe of reuenge, and taken for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune) in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy of our Prince, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Feuer againſt him.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>On fiery <hi>Rhamnuſias</hi> ſere, and ſulphurous ſpight,</l>
                     <l>who turn'd the ſterne orbs of her ghaſtly ſight,</l>
                     <l>About each corner of her vaſte Command,</l>
                     <l>And (in the turning of her bloudy hand)</l>
                     <l>Sought how to ruine endleſly our Hope,</l>
                     <l>And ſet to all miſhap all entries ope.<note place="margin">The Feuer the Prince died on (by <hi>Proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>a</hi>) d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by her effects &amp; circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſee how ready meanes to miſchiefe are;</l>
                     <l>She ſaw, faſt by, the bloud-affecting <hi>Feuer,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(Euen when th'Autumnal-ſtarre began t'expire)</l>
                     <l>Gathering in vapours thinne, Ethereall fire:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:19"/>
                     <l>Of which, her venomde finger did jmpart</l>
                     <l>To our braue Princes fount of heat, the heart;</l>
                     <l>A praeternaturall heat; which through the vaines</l>
                     <l>And Arteries, by'th blood and ſpirits meanes</l>
                     <l>Diffus'd about the body, and jnflam'd,</l>
                     <l>Begat a Feuor to be neuer nam'd.</l>
                     <l>And now this loather of the louely Light,</l>
                     <l>(Begot of <hi>Erebus,</hi> and vglie Night)</l>
                     <l>Mounted in haſt, her new, and noyſefull Carre,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe wheeles had beam-ſpokes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th'Hungarian ſtar;</l>
                     <l>And all the other frame, and freight; from thence<note place="margin">The Fever the Prince dyed off, is obſerv'd by our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions to bee begun in Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Deriu'd their rude and ruthleſſe jnfluence.</l>
                     <l>Vp to her left ſide, lept jnfernall Death</l>
                     <l>His head hid in a cloud of ſenſuall breath;</l>
                     <l>By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er ſat furious <hi>Anguiſh, Pale Deſpight;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Murmure,</hi> and <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and poſſeſt <hi>Affright;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yellow Corruption, Marow-eating Care;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Languor, chill Trembling, fits Irregulare;</l>
                     <l>Inconſtant Collor, <hi>feeble voyc't Complaint;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Relentles</hi> Rigor, and <hi>Confuſion</hi> faint;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Frantick Diſtemper;</hi> &amp; <hi>Hare-eyd vnrest;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Out of the property of the Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e that never ſhuts her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yes ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſhort-breath'd <hi>Thirſt,</hi> with th'euer-burning breaſt</l>
                     <l>A wreath of Adders bound her trenched Browes;</l>
                     <l>Where Torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Ambuſht lay with all her throws</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:20"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Marmarian Lyons,</hi> frindg'd with flaming <hi>Manes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Marmar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>cae Leone.,</hi> of <hi>Marmar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>a</hi> a Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ion in <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are bred; with which Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſd to bee drawn, for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, part of the effects of this Feuer. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the Feuer in theſe effects.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Drew this grym furie, and her brood of <hi>Banes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their hearts of glowing <hi>Coles,</hi> murmurd, &amp; ror'd,</l>
                     <l>To beare her crook't yokes, and her <hi>Banes</hi> abhord,</l>
                     <l>To their deare <hi>Prince,</hi> that bore them in his <hi>Armes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſhould not ſuffer, for his <hi>Good,</hi> their <hi>Harmes;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then from Hels burning whirlepit vp ſhe hallde,</l>
                     <l>The horrid <hi>Monſter</hi> fierce <hi>Echidna</hi> calde;</l>
                     <l>That from her <hi>Stigian Iawes,</hi> doth vomit ever,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quitture,</hi> and <hi>Venome,</hi> yet is empty neuer:</l>
                     <l>Then burnt her bloudſhot eyes, her <hi>Temples</hi> yet</l>
                     <l>Were cold as Ice, her Necke all drownd in ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Palenes</hi> ſpred all her breaſt, her lifes heat ſtung:</l>
                     <l>The Minds <hi>Interpreter,</hi> her ſcorched tongue,</l>
                     <l>Flowd with blew poiſon: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her yawning <hi>Mouth</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Rhumes fell like ſpouts fild fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtormy <hi>South:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which being corrupt, the hewe of <hi>Saffron</hi> tooke,</l>
                     <l>A feruent <hi>Vapor,</hi> all her body ſhooke:</l>
                     <l>From whence, her <hi>Vexed Spirits,</hi> a noyſome ſmell,</l>
                     <l>Expyr'd in fumes that lookt as blacke as <hi>Hell.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A ceaſeles Torrent did her <hi>Noſthrils</hi> ſteepe,</l>
                     <l>Her witherd Entrailes tooke no reſt, <hi>No ſleepe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her ſwoln throte ratl'd, warmd with lifes laſt ſpark</l>
                     <l>And in her ſalt jaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, painfull Cought did barke:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:20"/>
                     <l>Herteeth were ſtaind with Ruſt, her ſluttiſh hand</l>
                     <l>Shee held out reeking like a <hi>New-quencht Brand:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Arm'd with crook'd <hi>Tallons</hi> like the horned <hi>Moone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>All <hi>Cheere,</hi> all <hi>Eaſe,</hi> all <hi>Hope</hi> with her was gone:</l>
                     <l>In her left hand a quenchles fire did glow,</l>
                     <l>And in her <hi>Right Palme</hi> freez'd <hi>Sithonian</hi> Snow:</l>
                     <l>The ancient <hi>Romanes</hi> did a <hi>Temple</hi> build</l>
                     <l>To her, as whome a Deitie they held:</l>
                     <l>So hyd, and farre from cure of <hi>Man</hi> ſhee flyes,</l>
                     <l>In whoſe <hi>Lifes Power</hi> ſhe mater the Deities.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When fell <hi>Rhamnuſia</hi> ſaw this Monſter nere,</l>
                     <l>(Her ſteele <hi>Heart</hi> ſharpning) thus ſhe ſpake to her:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rhamnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Seeſt thou this <hi>Prince</hi> (great <hi>Maid</hi> &amp; ſeed of <hi>Night</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rows caſt beams about the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, like the <hi>Light:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who joyes ſecurely in all preſent <hi>State,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor dreams what <hi>Fortune</hi> is, or future <hi>Fate:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At whome, with fingers, and with fixed eyes</l>
                     <l>All Kingdomes <hi>Point,</hi> and <hi>Looke,</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Could be content to giue him: <hi>Templ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s</hi> rayſe</l>
                     <l>To his <hi>Expectance,</hi> and <hi>Vnbounded Praiſe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His <hi>Now-rip. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>irits,</hi> and <hi>Valor</hi> doth de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>piſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sickneſse,</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> that giue our <hi>Godheads</hi> Priſe:</l>
                     <l>His worth contracts the worlds, in his ſole <hi>Hope,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Religion, Vertue, Conqueſt</hi> haue no ſcope:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:21"/>
                     <l>But his Indowments; At him, at him, flie;</l>
                     <l>More ſwift, and timeleſſe, more the Deitie;</l>
                     <l>His Sommer, Winter with the jellid flakes;</l>
                     <l>His pure Life, poyſon, ſting out with thy Snakes;</l>
                     <l>This is a worke will Fame thy Maidenhead:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>am:</hi> durſt nolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger indure her, beeing ſtirred into furie.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>With this, her ſpeach and ſhe together fledde;</l>
                     <l>Nor durſt ſhe more endure her dreadfull eyes;</l>
                     <l>Who ſtung with goads her roaring Lyons thyes;</l>
                     <l>And brandiſht, round about, her Snak-curld head blew;</l>
                     <l>With her left hand, the Torch it managed.<note place="margin">The ſtarry Euening deſcrib'd by <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>lcans</hi> ſetting to worke at that time. The Night being ever chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſly cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ecrate to the Works of the Gods, and out of this Deities fires, the Starres are ſuppoſd to flye; as ſparkles of them.</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And now Heavens Smith, kindl'd his Forge &amp;</l>
                     <l>And through the round Pole, thick the ſparkls flew</l>
                     <l>When great Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi> the delight of fame;</l>
                     <l>Darkn'd the Pallace, of his Fathers Name,</l>
                     <l>And hid his white lyms, in his downie Bed;</l>
                     <l>Then Heaven wept falling Stars that ſummoned</l>
                     <l>(With ſoft, and ſilent Motion) ſleepe to breath</l>
                     <l>On his bright Temples, th'Ominous forme of death;</l>
                     <l>Which now the cruel Goddes did permit,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe might enter ſo, her Mayden fit;</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When the good Angell, his kind Guardian,</l>
                     <l>Her withet'd foot, ſaw neare this ſpring of Man;</l>
                     <l>He ſhrik't and ſaid; what, what are thy rude ends;<note place="margin">The good Angell of the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uce to the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as ſhee approach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cannot, in him alone, all vertues friends,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:21"/>
                     <l>(Melted into his all-vpholding Nerus;</l>
                     <l>For whoſe Aſſiſtance, euery Deity ſerues)</l>
                     <l>Mooue thee to proue thy Godhead, bleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing him</l>
                     <l>With long long life, whoſe light extinckt, wil dim,</l>
                     <l>All heavenly graces? all this, moou'd her nought;</l>
                     <l>But on, &amp; in his, all our rujnes wrought:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>She toucht the Threſholds, and the threſholds ſhooke;</l>
                     <l>The dore-poſts, <hi>Palenes</hi> pierſt with her faint look:</l>
                     <l>The dores brake open, and the fatall Bed</l>
                     <l>Rudely ſh'aproacht, &amp; thus her fell mouth ſaid;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Henrie,</hi> why tak'ſt thou thus thy reſt ſecure?<note place="margin">Feuer to the prince; who is thougght by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> friend of mine to ſpeake too mildly; not being <hi>ſatis compos m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi> in this. Her counſell or perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhewing onlie how the Prince was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded &amp; reſolu'd in his deadly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of her which ſhee is made to ſpeake in ſpight of her ſelfe, ſince he at her worſt was ſo ſacredly reſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nought doubting what Fortune &amp; fates aſſure;</l>
                     <l>Thou neuer yet felt'ſt my red right hands maims,</l>
                     <l>That I co thee, and fate to me proclaimes;</l>
                     <l>Thy fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſtands jdle; ſpinns no more thy thread;</l>
                     <l>Die thou muſt (great Prince) ſigh not; beare thy head</l>
                     <l>In all things free, even with neceſsity</l>
                     <l>If ſweet it be to liue; tis ſweet to dye:</l>
                     <l>This ſaid ſhee ſhooke at him her Torch, and caſt</l>
                     <l>A fire in him, that all his breaſt embrac't,</l>
                     <l>Then darting through his heart a deadly cold,</l>
                     <l>And as much venome as his vaines could holdj</l>
                     <l>Death, Death, O Death, inſerting, thruſting in,</l>
                     <l>Shut his faire eyes, and op't our vglie ſinne:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:22"/>
                     <l>This ſeene reſolu'd on, by her ſelfe and fate;</l>
                     <l>Was there a ſight ſo pale, and deſperate,</l>
                     <l>Euer before ſeene, in a thruſt-through State?</l>
                     <l>The poore <hi>Verginian,</hi> miſerable ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,<note place="margin">Deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>at caſt Sir <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>b. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>es</hi> on the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> &amp; the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>te of his Ship and Men, to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes Plight applyed in the Princes death.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> long-long-Night-turnd-Day, that liu'd in Hell</l>
                     <l>Neuer ſo portrayd, where the Billowes ſtroue</l>
                     <l>(Blackt like ſo many Devils) which ſhould proue</l>
                     <l>The damned Victor; all their furies heighting;</l>
                     <l>Their Drum, the thunder; &amp; their Colours light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</l>
                     <l>Both ſouldiers in the battel; one conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding</l>
                     <l>To drown the waues in Noyſe; the other ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding</l>
                     <l>His Hel-hot ſulphurous flames to drink the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dry:</l>
                     <l>When heaven was loſt, when not a teare wrackt eye,</l>
                     <l>Could tell in all that dead time, if they were,</l>
                     <l>Sincking or ſayling; till a quickning cleere</l>
                     <l>Gaue light to ſaue them by the ruth of Rocks</l>
                     <l>At the <hi>Bermudas;</hi> where the tearing ſhocks</l>
                     <l>And all the Miſeries before, more felt</l>
                     <l>Then here halfe told; All, All this did not melt</l>
                     <l>Thoſe deſperate few, ſtill dying more in teares,</l>
                     <l>Then this Death, all men, to the Marrow weares:</l>
                     <l>All that are Men; the reſt, thoſe drudging Beaſts,</l>
                     <l>That onely beare of Men, the Coates, and Creſts;</l>
                     <l>And for their Slaue, ſick, that can earne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pence,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:22"/>
                     <l>More mourne (O Monſters) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſuch a Prince;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſoules do ebbe &amp; flow ſtill with their gain,</l>
                     <l>Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing moues but pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f, &amp; their own pain;</l>
                     <l>Let ſuch (great Heauen) be onely borne to beare,</l>
                     <l>All that can follow this meere Maſſacre.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Loſt is our poore Prince; all his ſad jndure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s;</l>
                     <l>The buſie Art of thoſe that ſhould be Curers;</l>
                     <l>The ſacred vowes made by the zealous King,</l>
                     <l>His God-like Syre; his often viſiting;</l>
                     <l>Nor thy graue prayers and preſence (holy Man)<note place="margin">The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> paſſing py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in care of the Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. S. <hi>E de P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>l. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ps</hi> Maſter of the Rols and the Princes Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, a chieſe ſorrower for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>This Realme thrice Reverend Metropolitan,</l>
                     <l>That was the worthy Father to his ſoule:</l>
                     <l>Th'jnſulting Feuer could one fit controule.</l>
                     <l>Nor let me here forget on farre, and neare;</l>
                     <l>And in his lifes loue, Paſſing deepe and deare;</l>
                     <l>That doth his ſacred <hi>Memorie</hi> adore,</l>
                     <l>Virtues true favtor his graue <hi>Chancellor,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe worth in all workes ſhould a <hi>Place</hi> enioie,</l>
                     <l>Where his fit <hi>Fame</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er <hi>Trumpet</hi> ſhall jmploie,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe <hi>Cares,</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> were euer vſde to eaſe</l>
                     <l>His feu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rous Warre, &amp; ſend him health full peace,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſicke our <hi>Prince</hi> is ſtill; who though the ſteps</l>
                     <l>Of bitter <hi>Death,</hi> he ſaw bring in by heaps</l>
                     <l>Clouds to his <hi>Luſter,</hi> and poore reſt of light;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:23"/>
                     <l>And felt his laſt Day ſuffering laſting Night;</l>
                     <l>His true-bred-braue ſoule, ſhrunck yet at no part,</l>
                     <l>Downe kept he all ſighs, with his powers al-Hart;<note place="margin">The prince heroical his bearing his ſicknes at the Kings comming to ſee him, careful not to diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him. The Twelfth day after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                              <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>cke, his ſicknes was held <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cler'd euen his dying browes: and (in an Eye</l>
                     <l>Manly diſſembling) hid his Miſery.</l>
                     <l>And all to ſpare the Royall heat ſo ſpent</l>
                     <l>In his ſad Father, fearefull of th'event.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And now did <hi>Phoebus</hi> with his Twelfth Lampe ſhow</l>
                     <l>The world his haples light: and in his Brow</l>
                     <l>A Torch of Pitch ſtuck, lighting halfe t'half skies,</l>
                     <l>When lifes laſt error preſt the broken eyes</l>
                     <l>Of this heart-breaking Prince; his forc't look fled;</l>
                     <l>Fled was all Colour from his cheekes; yet fed</l>
                     <l>His ſpirit, his ſight: with dying now, he caſt</l>
                     <l>On his kind King, and Father: on whome, faſt</l>
                     <l>He fixt his fading beames: and with his view</l>
                     <l>A little did their empty Orbs renew:</l>
                     <l>His Mind ſaw him, come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deeps of Death,<note place="margin">The prince dying to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he King.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To whome he ſaid, O Author of my Breath:</l>
                     <l>Soule to my life, and eſſence to my Soule,</l>
                     <l>Why grieue you ſo, that ſhould al griefe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troule?</l>
                     <l>Death's ſweet to me, that you are ſtil lifes creature,</l>
                     <l>I now haue finiſht the great worke of Nature.</l>
                     <l>I ſee you pay a perfect Fathers debt</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:23"/>
                     <l>And in a feaſtfull Peace your Empire kept;</l>
                     <l>If your true Sonnes laſt words haue any right</l>
                     <l>In your moſt righteous Boſome, doe not fright</l>
                     <l>your hearkning kingdoms to your cariage now;</l>
                     <l>All yours, in mee, I here reſigne to you,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My youth (I pray to God with my laſt powres</hi>)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Subſtract from me may adde to you and yours.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus vaniſht he, thus ſwift, thus inſtantly;</l>
                     <l>Ah now I ſee, euen heauenly powres muſt dye.<note place="margin">The ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and bemones of the King Queene, Prince and his moſt Princely Siſter, for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces death.</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now ſhift the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queene</hi> from court to court</l>
                     <l>but no way can ſhift off their cares reſort,</l>
                     <l>That which we hate the more vve flie, purſues,</l>
                     <l>that which we loue, the more we ſeek, eſchewes:</l>
                     <l>Now weepes his Princely <hi>Brother;</hi> Novv alas</l>
                     <l>His Cynthian <hi>Siſter,</hi> (our ſole earthly Grace)</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Hebes</hi> fount ſtill ouerflowes her bounds,</l>
                     <l>And in her colde lips, ſtick aſtoniſht ſounds,</l>
                     <l>Sh'oppreſſeth her ſweet kinde; In her ſoft breſt</l>
                     <l>Care can no vent finde, it is ſo compreſt:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And ſee hovv the Promethean Liuer growes<note place="margin">The fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As vulture Griefe deuoures it: ſee freſh ſhowes</l>
                     <l>Reuiue woes ſence, and multiply her ſoule;</l>
                     <l>And worthely; for vvho would teares controle</l>
                     <l>On ſuch a ſpringing ground? Tis dearely fit,</l>
                     <l>To pay all tribute, Thought can poure on it:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:24"/>
                     <l>For vvhy vvere Funerals firſt vs'd but for theſe,</l>
                     <l>Preſag'd and caſt in their Natiuities?</l>
                     <l>The ſtreames were checkt a while: ſo Torrents ſtaid</l>
                     <l>Enrage the more; but are (left free) allaid.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now our grim waues march altogether; Now</l>
                     <l>Our blacke ſeas runne ſo high, they ouerflow</l>
                     <l>the clouds they nouriſh; now the gloomy herſe</l>
                     <l>Puts out the Sunne: Reuiue, reuiue (dead vierſe)</l>
                     <l>death hath ſlain death; there ther the perſon lies</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe death ſhould buy out all mortalities.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But let the world be now a heape of death,</l>
                     <l>Lifes ioy lyes dead in him, and challengeth</l>
                     <l>No leſſe a reaſon: If all motion ſtoode</l>
                     <l>Benumb'd and ſtupified, with his frozen blood;</l>
                     <l>And like a Tombe-ſtone, fixt, lay all the ſeas</l>
                     <l>There were fit pillers for our Hercules</l>
                     <l>To bound the world with: Men had better dye</l>
                     <l>Then out-liue free times; ſlaues to Policie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>On on ſad Traine, as from a crannid rocke</l>
                     <l>Bee-ſwarmes rob'd of their honey, ceaſles flock.</l>
                     <l>Mourne, mourne, diſſected now his cold lims lie</l>
                     <l>Ah, knit ſo late vvith flame, and Maieſtie.</l>
                     <l>where's now his gracious ſmile, his ſparkling eie</l>
                     <l>His Iudgement, Valour, Magnanimitie?</l>
                     <l>O God, what doth not one ſhort hour ſnatch vp</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4165:24"/>
                     <l>Of all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>loſſe? ſtill ouer-flowes the cup</l>
                     <l>Of his burſt cares; put with no nerues together,</l>
                     <l>And lighter, then the ſhadow of a feather.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>On: make earth pomp as frequent as ye c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>'Twill ſtill leaue black, the faireſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ower of man,</l>
                     <l>Yee vvell may lay all coſt on miſerie,</l>
                     <l>Tis all can boaſt, the proud'ſt humanitie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If yong <hi>Marcellus</hi> had to grace his fall,</l>
                     <l>Sixe hundred Herſes at his Funerall;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sylla</hi> ſixe thouſand; l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t Prince <hi>Henry</hi> haue</l>
                     <l>Sixe Millions bring him to his greedy graue.</l>
                     <l>And now the States of earth, thus mourn below</l>
                     <l>Behold in Heauen, <hi>Loue</hi> with his broken Bow;</l>
                     <l>his quiuer downwards turn'd, his brands put out</l>
                     <l>Hanging his wings; with ſighes all black about.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor leſſe, our loſſe, his Mothers heart infeſts,</l>
                     <l>Her melting palmes, beating her ſnowy breſts;</l>
                     <l>As much confus'd, as when the Calidon Bore</l>
                     <l>The thigh of her diuine <hi>Adonis</hi> tore:</l>
                     <l>Her vowes all vaine, reſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'d to bleſſe his yeeres</l>
                     <l>VVith Iſſue Royall, and exempt from freres,</l>
                     <l>Who now dyed fruitleſſe; and preuented then</l>
                     <l>The bleſt of women, of the beſt of men.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Mourne all ye Arts, ye are not of the earth;</l>
                     <l>Fall, fall with him; riſe with his ſecond birth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4165:25"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
